this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
[Music]
need a helping hand with your system's
architecture software mill will help you
design
high throughput back-ends and
event-driven solutions
we're a brand trusted by businesses and
valued by employees due to our remote
first transparent organization which
gives back to the it community through
education and open source
have an idea let's code together meet
our scala
java kafka and typescript engineers at
softwaremail.com today
hello everyone this is felina for
software engineering radio
today on the show with me is marco faela
he is a professor of computer science at
the university of naples federico
secundo
in italy marco has contributed to the
palma plunheedra library a well-known
scientific library
for symbolic manipulation of polyhedra
he has taught classes on java
programming
pilot construction and software
engineering to undergraduate and
graduate students since 2005.
marco is also the author of today's
topic the book
seriously good software welcome to the
show marco
hi thank you very much for hosting me
you're welcome so your book is called
seriously good software i think that's
something that we all strive for
but what is good exactly
what do you mean by seriously good
software
i was trying to fill a gap that i
felt in uh some types of computer
science education
i have the impression that a lot of
people come into programming with
a sort of uh simplistic view of of the
job where
you just have to find a way
of achieving a certain task achieving a
goal that that you've been giving
and without a global
view of the different forces of the
different qualities
that software may or may not have
without without a view of the
trade-offs that that are involved in in
writing good software so that was the
starting point for
for the book and uh in particular i
think that
a lot of curricula have uh very deep
classes and talking about especially
computer science curricula have deep
classes about specific topics like
algorithms or operating systems and so
on
but i think students may end up with
with a very vertical view of different
topics and without a global overview of
their relationships and how to
compare and contrast these different
techniques
and and when it's more appropriate to
focus on on one aspect versus another
aspect of the software so i try
to provide a more horizontal let's say
point of view across disciplines across
topics yeah i want to zoom into that
vertical and horizontal a little bit
because
it might not be clear to all of our
listeners what exactly you mean by that
so
could you briefly point out what's
vertical and what horizontal mean here
yes let me give you a brief overlook of
the book for
for for our listeners uh so the idea is
the following for for this book i have
uh
one single example that's developed
in many different ways along the book
and in each chapter i focus on a
different software quality for
for instance i have a a chapter on time
efficiency then i have
a chapter on memory efficiency and i
keep
refactoring the same example with
respect to different
objectives with with respect to
different software qualities
and trying to emphasize the trade-offs
between them and so that's what i call
horizontal it's
it's across this across you have a
little bit of algorithms
data structures operating systems
concurrency
uh software engineering mixed
together uh and compared on the exam on
the same example
whereas by vertical i mean the classical
classical computer science curriculum
where you you take
a full class on algorithms and you focus
an entire semester something like that
on big o complexity
and the fastest way to do certain things
yeah so what you're saying i think is
that
university often prepares students for
really deep tasks like algorithms or
databases but what sometimes might be
missing from a curriculum is how to
apply them and how to make the right
selection of
what to use where is that a fair summary
of the problem that the book addresses
yeah yeah absolutely so you mentioned
this already a little bit is that your
book talks about different
qualities that software can have and
while reading the book
i found it hard to really define what a
quality
is so can you briefly explain what is a
before going into detail of course into
the different qualities that the book
talked about
sure so by quality i
i know it's a very uh general term uh i
mean
any desirable property of software any
desirable property that a piece of
software may or may not have
or may have to a different degree and
and most of these properties
are traditionally called non-functional
requirements
but i'm not fond of this functional
versus non-functional
distinction i have to say i think most
of these properties
they become so when you say the property
is non-functional
it sounds to me as if you are
diminishing its importance you're saying
it's optional it's
it's non-functional whereas i think
they're they're important i think most
of them
in fact become functional properties
beyond
a certain threshold for example take
time performance time performance is
usually in most systems a non-functional
property because you don't care whether
uh your software gives you a service in
one millisecond or two milliseconds
most of the time of course it depends on
on the context but most of the time you
don't care
but still even if it's uh i don't know
even if it's
if it's a user oriented service that an
interactive
program well you may not care about one
millisecond versus two milliseconds but
you certainly care that uh that that
service
works within one second or works within
one minute
and if you get that service in one hour
instead of one second
of course that very poor performance
becomes a functional issue
and i think this applies to most
non-functional so-called
non-functional requirements they can all
become functional
beyond a certain threshold if
if they're not properly satisfied yeah
so to summarize i think what you're
saying is that qualities are
quite related to non-functional
requirements but that you're not fond of
this non-functional term because it
seems to indicate
no importance or non-core to design
whereas
you rightly point out that even
something like
reliability or time optimization can get
functional
once it gets too much out of hand yes
yes it's it's
uh it's a thin this distinction it's
uh yeah a requirement can jump from one
side to the other quite easily
it's not it's not clear-cut
yeah yeah i actually think that's a
really important distinction where we
try to say this is functional and this
is not
functional but it isn't as binary as
that
it is possible for these two to move
over the spectrum of
from functional to non-functional so i'm
wondering
what was your goal in describing these
qualities
so so why was it needed to formulate the
book
in that way along these lines of these
different qualities
what does that add first of all
i think it adds it adds awareness
to to programmers and and of course the
book is mainly intended for
junior programmers or people fresh out
of their
school or their computer science or
other
kind of uh of school and uh
organizing the book uh around these
qualities
i mean at least my intent was to
make them aware of this
different points of view on software on
this
different requirements they may have to
to satisfy
give them a let's say in a way a
vocabulary of
of of qualities to think about
so i'm i'm very
focused on this awareness idea so
before you can improve your software
before you can write good software
first of all you have to be aware that
that there's a problem or
you have to be aware that there's
different ways to
measure in in the best case or evaluate
somehow
your software there's different point of
views
then only then you you should be aware
of the techniques that you can use to to
improve those qualities
and finally on a kind of a third level
you should have the experience and the
capacity to judge
which quality to focus on among all
those qualities that
are always present somehow so your
software
has to do its job that's the
correctness that's the functional
requirements then it has to do it in
an efficient manner and so on and so
forth
so you have to be aware of these
dimensions then you have to know
specific techniques to work
on those dimensions to improve on those
dimensions
and then finally you or your co-workers
or your boss
have to have the vision to pick
uh the right balance among these
properties
yeah so it adds a vocabulary to help
people to make the right
decisions and you mentioned trade-offs
also earlier in the show
between all of those qualities one more
thing
this this this idea is also an
invitation to improve specifications
because i think often specifications
focus too much on the functional aspects
and too little
on those other requirements whereas
after the fact
perhaps during development or perhaps
after deployment or at some point you
realize
that you overlooked some non-functional
requirement that turns out to be
important and
and perhaps it turns out to be
functional it turns out to be
crucial so another
direction where i hope the book can can
improve the standard practices is to
improve specifications
and push people to be more
uh complete in their specifications to
include these uh so-called
non-functional requirements in the
initial
industry in the software specifications
explicitly
oh yeah i really like that i i like that
where you're saying this isn't only
relevant for the process of creating
software
it can also be important for the process
of
specifying and designing software that's
also where you can
use these qualities as maybe something
like a checklist even have we thought
about
all these six qualities right yeah
exactly
as a reminder yeah well what do we need
about space efficiency do we need
anything
what do we need about readability that
that's a tricky part but
yeah so i think it's now time to zoom
into the
qualities i would like to go over them
one by one
where we can talk about what is the
quality maybe you also have examples of
code bases in which this quality did
well or didn't well so i would like to
start with time efficiency
this is one that has come up already a
bunch of times there's really a
difference between
a query taking one second and a query
taking one hour
so what is your definition of time
efficiency
well uh of course uh time efficiency is
simply uh achieving your task in
uh as little time as possible
and uh i think it needs very little
introduction to
any programmer i think most programmers
are naturally
interested in it perhaps uh too much
and so putting it as my first quality is
a kind of trick to to get people
interested in the book because i know
that so many programmers are are just
passionate and fascinated by
time efficiency there we i mean i i'm
one of them and i'm so happy when you
when you manage to to to get a big speed
up on
on on your implementation it's great
it's great for everyone so
in its very little introduction just if
you want a specific example or a small
anecdote
just these days i was browsing twitter
and
a guy was complaining about the reaction
time
when he clicks on the right mouse button
on windows in most cases you get some
kind of
context aware menu so it depends on
where you click
on your desktop on your uh start menu
you get some sort of special menu when
you click on the
right button right mouse button and he
noticed that
uh on the modern hardware modern machine
sometimes you need to wait for i don't
know one second or two seconds to get
that menu and and he thought that was
uh uh crazy and uh i think
i kind of agree with him i mean it's one
of the basic user interactions for
for for windows or any operating system
these days so
it should be really fast it should be
instantaneous from your point of view
so the operating system and and other
software that's
that's cooperating with it should cache
those lines before you even click on the
right
button and it should come out
immediately
and uh and so i mean this
it was interesting because then this guy
went into
a very deep debugging of the issue and
uh
he was very a capable debugger he he
could find
the source for for this lag and he
i think he posted some some bug report
on windows and
i think maybe they're working on it or
maybe they already fixed it i don't know
but uh that's that's a very simple
example
of something that we all interact with
and um
perhaps we're used to it we're used to
having to wait a couple of seconds
uh to get that menu but it it
shouldn't be like that i mean there's no
reason why a modern
uh i don't know eight core five
gigahertz machine
should have you uh wait a couple of
seconds
to to show a list of 10 items or 20
items
yeah well actually um well i i you said
in the beginning that the time
efficiency might be an
easy thing to measure however i do think
it's it's more complicated than it used
to be and
now that you got me thinking of this
context menu i
also recently was wondering why it was
so slow and then i realized that one of
the reasons it's slow is that if you're
connected to dropbox
then dropbox will go to the internet to
see if you're actually connected and if
you are
you get extra elements in your context
menu you get like
share this link on dropbox or stuff like
that so something
where we might oh this is a local
operation
and the operating system should be able
to do this really quickly
yeah oftentimes nowadays there's also
some network
connectivity in places where you don't
necessarily expect it so
maybe time efficiency used to be easy
because you could just look at your
source code and sort of
count the number of iterations in your
for loop but now that we have async 08
so i think from my perspective time
efficiency
was easier in the old days than it is
now do you
agree and this is something that the
book also talks about the differences
between
measuring efficiency in your own code
base and
having stuff in different places
um yeah that's a very good uh very good
observation so
in the specific case of the context menu
i'm sure there's
there's a rather complex architecture
behind it
because as you mentioned different
programs can
plug in into that into that menu and uh
and add their own stuff still i mean
you have the example of dropbox checking
on the internet whether
yeah whether it's connected or not but
perhaps the then the architecture should
be
changed or should perhaps
i mean i'm sure there's good there's
reasons
to be like it is but
there's nothing preventing the
architecture to have dropbox
check the connection beforehand even
before on the background before you
click
and then when you click it just gives
you the latest
status and if the latest status is
unconnected then
too bad it's unconnected and you will
click again and maybe
you are you're more lucky but perhaps
dropbox could
update every i don't know 10 times a
second
this uh this little cache of of items
anyway uh in general about the book
and what i do about time efficiency i
don't have the space
uh uh to to cover all these
very interesting uh aspects you
mentioned like
uh difference between doing something
locally
or having some uncontrollable lag in
between
that's that's certainly an interesting
issue practically
on the other hand again since
since the book tries to cover all of
these different topics
in a short amount in certain number of
pages it's like a 300 page book
which tries to cover from algorithms to
software engineering
and so on and so forth so it should be
clear that every chapter is just a short
introduction to the topic so for
for every chapter for every topic for
every software quality
i don't go into the details but rather i
give a uh an overview
of the topic i applied to my uh
recurring
example and then i applied to some other
examples
and then i give pointers to uh
to other great books where readers can
really fill in the rest fill in the
details so
it's really works like that due to space
constraints
yeah yeah of course we understand that
even the book is limited and this
episode is even more limited in time but
if you could share with us just
like one takeaway from time efficiency
what is the most
important thing that our our audience
should realize when considering time
efficiency of application
right um so there's a little there's
um it's not like a great
uh discovery but it's uh a little
observation that
uh perhaps is not present
in uh traditional discussions about time
efficiency so
so the whole book i i in the whole book
i focus on
small code samples not large systems
just i focus on single classes and most
of the time
when you study algorithms in school
at university you focus on a single
input output function so you want to
given a graph you want to output i don't
know the shortest path from one vertex
to another vertex so
simple input output problems given this
input
produce this output and that's great and
and on that kind of problems you can
apply all the asymptotic
analysis complexity analysis asymptotic
notation and so on
my small observation is that in practice
even on a single class so even on
even in a very small unit you have
different methods operating on on that
class
and each method may have a different
complexity so
you you may have some one method taking
linear time another method
does something more complex takes
quadratic time and so on
and and my little observation is is that
sometimes
you cannot optimize uh the complexity of
all methods at the same time
sometimes you have to choose you can
make one method faster
at the cost of another method becoming
slower
so that's another level of trade-off
that you may have between
different methods within a single
quality which is time performance you
may
have to find a balance between the
complexity of different methods
that's something that that's shown in
the book
great yeah that is a good thing to take
away that you can magically make stuff
better often if you make something
better
here then you might actually worsen
somewhere and something in another place
of the code base so i do think that's a
a good relocation to make yeah and i
make this observation on a small unit
because that's the style of the book but
you can
apply the same observation to larger
systems where sometimes
you can make one uh feature or
one module faster at the expense of
another one that's going to be slower
yeah yeah this also um the same can be
generalized from
uh two methods to two classes or two
modules or two microservices that
are at all with each other right
then the next quality is quite related
is
space efficiency so there too i was
wondering
you know what is your definition and do
you have another great anecdote of
space efficiency and how it's how it is
impacting performance of
code bases right so um yes space
efficiency
of course by space i i mean memory
occupancy so
basic definition would be well okay this
is
already a little bit trickier because a
very basic definition would be to
use as little memory as possible
that's uh that's a very simple
definition but
that's usually not what you want in in
in software development
so a better definition would be make
good use
of the memory of of the memory you
occupy but of course
that's a better definition but it's also
more vague
because what do you mean by good use let
me let me
here uh make a my favorite example about
space efficiency to to clarify a little
bit
so my favorite example is video games
i think video games are a fascinating
pieces of software
not only as a player but also as a
programmer and as a
professor and in fact i'm also teaching
a game development class
so they're very complex uh they're very
complex software systems and
one of the characteristics of video
games is that
no matter how much memory your
architecture
your device has you can be sure that
there are video games that people will
write video games that will saturate
that capacity that will saturate
the whole computational power of your
device
and perhaps even when you come up with a
new architecture a new console a gaming
console or a new device
even before the device comes out there's
already video games in production being
produced that saturate
the capacity of that machine and the
same can be said about
graphic cards of course and and this has
always been true like from from the
first video games like
space war from from the 60s and the
pdp computer to to the latest games it's
always been like that so
video games really push the hardware to
its limits and in particular they push
the
the the memory they they fill up the
memory
uh and they always have a lot more data
that can be fit into memory so
so in video games you find that uh that
there's a lot of effort
to exploit all the memory available to
push
as much data as possible in ram as much
data as possible in the video memory and
so on and so forth
and what happens when you try to squeeze
as much information as possible into
your memory is that you start to use
special encodings for data and that's
something i also show in the book so
perhaps you have a small integers
so you you take a 32-bit
integer and you put two
16-bit integers into one even if your
language doesn't have a
short data type for instance so you
start using
crazy representations that squeeze
as much information as possible into
your
bits so you you try to in other words
you try to exploit
every single bit in your memory no bit
is wasted
and that's uh that's very interesting
that's uh that's an interesting exercise
that's also a very extreme
path that you should in practice you
should only take
if uh if you have no other choice
because when you start using those crazy
ad hoc
representations you lose on many other
software qualities you are probably
losing the readability
because your software becomes tricky to
read and
understand and therefore you're losing
maintainability
you're decreasing your maintainability
and so on and so forth so taken to the
extreme
space space efficiency is a is very
uh drastic measure it's it's uh
it really conflicts with with other
software qualities on the other hand
in a normal program you don't want to
use too much memory without a good
reason
so without going into those extreme
representations
it's still good to have general
understanding
of how much memory a hash table
takes compared to how much memory an
array takes
in most implementation a hash table of
course it's
it's much more much more efficient for
many operations but
it's also many times larger than a
simple array
those are the kind of simple comparisons
that
that every programmer should be should
be aware of regardless of the specific
domain calling all developers
there's no telling what you can create
when you upgrade your data platform to
intersystems iris
are you ready to build the applications
you want however you want them
are you ready to develop applications
faster than ever collaborate
build faster and deploy more efficiently
tomorrow's next breakthroughs are
waiting for you today
intersystems iris data platform ready
set code start coding for free visit
intersystems.com
try to try iris
yeah i really like this example of games
because it
it's sort of reversed right normally you
just you have what you want to make and
then it takes up the memory
or the the space that you have
but then for a game it's just this is
the memory and this is the hard disk
size you have to fill and you're just
going to fill it as efficiently as
possible so
i think that's an excellent example of a
domain a space where this space
efficiency
is just it's just really really core and
it's
it maybe overpowers other dimension one
one thing you just mentioned and
this is a nice segue into the next
quality you said sometimes being really
space efficient
like using a very special encoding comes
to the detriment of readability and
readability is also
one of the qualities that are in the
book so of course here we also want to
know
what is readability and can you share
another of those anecdotes or domains
about
readability and to contextualize it
readability is is
a kind of hypothetical measure
because you can't really measure it in
any easy way but
in principle you try to imagine the
effort
needed to understand that code
particularly
for someone who hasn't written it but
as we all know as all programmers know
even your own code if you don't look at
it for
a couple of months it's basically as if
it was written by someone else you you
you quickly forget the mental model
that you that that brought you to that
piece of code
and therefore you basically have to
start from scratch as if someone else
wrote that piece of code
and and the amount of effort you need to
put
in into understanding that code is is
called
readabilities is related to its
readability
and and uh the readability i think it's
a very interesting
quality very different from from from
the first two we talked about
so time and space efficiency just
because
it's so hard to measure at the same time
it's
also very important and the reason it's
very important is that
this readability is in in turn
is a proxy for maintainability so
maintainability means
how easy it is to modify
to fix to extend your program
and of course every commercial software
needs to evolve in time it needs to be
uh it needs to have bug fixed
it needs to be extended and so on so
uh having a code that is easy to read
and understand
is a good proxy to its future
maintainability the easier it is to read
generally speaking the easier it is to
modify it
without introducing new bugs because you
understand it because
you managed to understand it and you
know what you're doing
on the other hand i noticed that it's at
the same time
i think it's very important as a quality
but at the same time there's
little effort in academia and or in
general
in schools in programming schools
towards this
objective this little very little effort
in teaching
readability and once again that that's
because
it's not a fully developed topic
it's not easy to measure and it's not
there's no well-developed theory of
readability
so what we have are examples what we
have are guidelines
and in fact that that's what i focus on
in the book because that's
the best we have right now i'm thinking
about
the famous refactoring rules by martin
fowlers and robert martin's
clean code guidelines so those are
practical
uh time-tested guidelines that are very
successful in practice but they
they're they don't constitute a uh
an overall theory okay it's a set of
guidelines
they work well in practice and
lots of people agree with them and
i think they're very valuable but we
don't have a systematic theory
there i know there's people trying to
measure there's people in academia
trying to
actually measure readability sometimes i
even read like scientific papers about
uh taking brain scans
of people reading code to
try to scientifically measure the effort
they're putting into understanding it
but i don't think this is like extreme
attempts
are going to to to solve our problem i
think we have
i think we need the as a discipline we
need time
to figure this out to establish a
consensus
over what's readable code and also i
think
at some point it becomes a little
subjective so that at some point
you cannot have uh you cannot have a
hundred percent
agreement on the rules of uh of uh
readable software at some point it
becomes
uh subjective what's the the better
style
yeah i think you're making lots of
interesting points there that i want to
follow up on
so yeah definitely of course it isn't
possible to measure the readability of
code in the same way
as space efficiency as time efficiency
so maybe
different things would be needed and i
think it's really interesting that you
said
as a field we don't really have a good
theory
for readability of code i think i agree
with you there but i'm wondering
how would such a theory look like what
are the
the boundary conditions of such a theory
what is the thing
what is the thing we're missing there
from resources like uh like refactoring
we have a bunch of things so what are we
missing
right so let me mention a couple more
things that we
do have that of course you're well aware
of but
let me mention them nevertheless so we
have a lot
of proxy measures like cyclomatic
complexity
method length simply you know um
we we say that methods should be short
no more than
i don't know 20 lines something like
that so lots of people
uh have proposed different
metrics so it's numbers it's something
easy
to measure and then they try to connect
these numbers this quantitative
objective measures
to some other independent
measure of readability like asking
someone after
he or she has read a piece of code so
they asked them
how easy was it to understand or maybe
what what does this code do please
please describe it or
answer this question about the code and
so on and they
correlate these measures to the answers
to do to the questionnaire
to the answers given by the person i i
think that's a very reasonable way to
proceed and
i know that we have some results
even though you know you're comparing
something objective and measurable
okay that's everyone agrees what's the
cyclomatic complexity of a given
function okay you just
count the number of nested loops on
nested
conditionals and so on but on the other
hand you are comparing it with the
subjective judgments made by people
which means
that sometimes one paper will
will claim something and then another
paper can claim
almost the opposite because it asks the
questions in a slightly different way to
their subjects to the or maybe the
people answering the questions are
different
have a different level of experience so
it's very hard to reach a consensus this
way
but i don't see any other way to move
forward i think it is the right way but
we need time to establish like standard
protocols for these experiments then
maybe we can move
towards consensus about what are
the best metrics what metrics
correlate to the best with actual
readability with
people people's effort to understand
code
yeah or if i may offer an alternative
theory
or an alternative suggestion maybe we
should accept that these two qualities
or the like time and space efficiency
and on the other hand readability
are just different things and the
philosopher thomas kuhn has this idea of
incremental ability that it's just
impossible
to measure two things with the same
framework and i think maybe one of the
mistakes that people make here
is that they try to reduce readability
to also being a number
whereas an alternative way could be just
to to accept the fact that some things
can be measured
in the number and other things are
vague like is this art piece nice well
it depends
on a number of things including personal
taste so
we can we can try to make the one more
numeric or we can try to accept that
maybe it isn't very numeric yeah yeah i
agree
and to move on to another quality you
also have the quality
reusability and reusability might suffer
from the same
issue as readability that reusability is
also hard to quantify so
again i want to hear what your
perspective is on what
is reusability and how do we how
do do we measure it should we measure it
and if we want to how would we do that
so by reusability perhaps also
generalities
is a good word for this for this quality
i mean
how easy is it to take your
implementation and once again i focus on
small units so let's talk about a single
class how easy
it is to pick your class and put it in a
partially or completely different
context
in a different system and make it useful
there
may make it useful in another another
context
so uh my perspective on this is that uh
focusing on this quality first of all is
simply
a great opportunity to learn something
so what i mean is it gives rise to very
interesting programming exercises for
for people who are learning
for example you you can tell them pick
pick some class that
that you uh designed and turn it into a
library
that's that's the most reusable that's
what we call
completely reusable code we call it a
library that's that's the code that's
meant and intended from day one to be
put in completely different contexts and
still be useful in different contexts
so i think i think that's a very useful
exercise for for people
learning to program and because
what do you do and and this also happens
in the book is that
you take this class it has some data of
course
you have to pick the right class you
have to pick a class that's
amenable to being generalized but if you
pick uh
if you pick a good class then this class
will have data of course
we'll have operations methods and if you
think about turning it into a library
you'll probably want to generalize
the kind of data it supports it contains
and then of course you want to
generalize the operations so what you
end up doing is
probably start from some concrete data
types that are in the class
and you're probably going to replace
them by type parameters
so you're going to use generics in in
java terms or templates in in c plus
plus language and so on
and then you have to generalize the
operations and that's also a very useful
uh exercise because you probably end up
using
interfaces complex interfaces to
represent what this abstract
data type is capable of doing
and therefore you end up using
what are in java called the bounded type
parameters
bounded wild cards so these pretty
advanced
language features that you don't get to
use every day
in this kind of of context they will
come
handy i think also c plus plus is adding
this
this year c plus plus uh 2020
should add something called traits or
concepts maybe
are they called traitor concepts i'm not
sure that's that's related to this
that's uh that's a new kind of
abstraction
to generalize to have a very expressive
way of generalizing
operations to multiple data types so
it's it's something that
leads to using interesting and advanced
language features that that's useful for
for learners whereas in practice
on the job i think that the
the situation is quite reversed because
in practice i think programmers
are too keen to generalize their
software
so they're known most programmers are
known to
over generalize their software whereas
in practice on the job when you have
little time
to achieve your goal it's perfectly fine
to write your
context specific class in in in a rather
non-reusable way so you
should distinguish uh theory and the
learning
stage from uh in this case i
i mean in most cases with usability i
would
be careful about pushing reusability
in practice like like on the job unless
of course you are
actually developing a library then
that's your primary goal
usability should be your primary goal
well actually i really like this
this frame of thinking i think it's a
really great question you could ask to
students but also people within a
company
if this would become a library what what
changes would you make now
and just to get people in the mindset of
reusability
this might also enable reuse if people
would write their code in a more
reusable way then
maybe more reuse would happen so this i
mean this is i think for me
now already to highlight from this
interview because now i'm thinking of my
own code base
i'm like oh but what if part of this
would be a library then what changes
would i make so
i actually think that's a really really
good way and also a concrete way of
i think the designing libraries is a lot
of fun for experienced programmers but
it may be a nightmare for for junior
programmers
yeah but then it is a nightmare that you
know they need to
get used to at one point because you are
going to release something either as a
open source library or there will be
someone in your company that says oh
you've done this before can i
can i look at your code or can i reuse
your code so it is
it is good to practice it because it
might occur it's likely to occur later
in life
once again when i say maybe a nightmare
to uh
to junior developers once again i mean
it's not their fault i mean
it's our fault as educators i think
that's that's another area where
in my experience in academia we don't
put
enough enough stress and focus on
designing good apis which is a crucial
part of designing a library
we focus uh a lot on uh
designing algorithms and implementing
them that's great
then and on good data structures it's
also great since
and but
i think we focus too little on apis and
uh larger scale issues or
reusability issues yeah we have two more
qualities left but this was actually one
of the questions i still had on my list
so let's let's zoom into this a little
bit more
because why don't we teach that i mean
you're a professor and i'm professor we
have
limited power to to change this why do
you think it is that most universities
also like my university why don't we
teach this
like is it too hard i don't i don't even
know myself why i don't
pay more attention to this well
obviously we have little time right so
so we have to make a choice and uh
i think a lot of it is tradition so some
some areas like algorithms and
i mean i'm totally uh
fond of algorithms algorithm theory and
i've also worked
research-wise on different types of
algorithms so
i completely appreciate
the area and
algorithms and data structures they
like they have a first of all they have
a longer a somewhat longer history than
software engineering this this this
other concerns we are talking about
like good apis and reusability they they
would be called software engineering
topics and software engineering is uh is
a little younger than
than the more established areas like
algorithm and data structures i would
say
because software engineering came with
large systems and
large systems took more time to be
developed
than single algorithms
so there's there's tradition there's
areas that have a stronger tradition
than
and also those areas are more
mathematical
and and therefore they have a more
developed
theory or overall organic theory and
that's
uh that's somehow easier to teach
and also easier to test yeah yeah i
definitely think that testing has
something to do with it
it's also easier to it's easier to
create examples for algorithms like
here's a two by two matrix and now you
have to multiply it with something else
or
here's a here's a maze and you have to
find the shortest path
or the the best way to run through this
map and everything is
more yeah everything is more is simpler
in the in the sense that it's easier to
compare to algorithms you
you have all the structure to you have
asymptotical analysis it's precise it's
mathematical it gives you
as uh it gives you an exact answer to
the question which of these two
algorithms is better
whereas if you're asking which of these
two apis is better
that's a completely different better it
comes back to the measurability
right also when a student involves the
solution we can say you have to do this
within five seconds
otherwise your answer is wrong or yeah
you can just use
10 megabytes of memory whereas with
readability
yeah it's way harder to judge and maybe
the student has really good arguments to
do something in a certain way and then
yeah sometimes you might even
vince i mean i've had discussions with
co-workers where i was really like
why would you do it like this and then
they say well because this is this and
you're like
oh well this is not my opinion but this
is actually
also a reasonable stand name so it might
really have to do with this
measurability as well where it's just
really hard
to judge if a statement is doing it
right and then in addition of course
also the things you mentioned
lacking a good theoretical framework
probably lacking enough faculty that
have enough understanding of this to
teach it
and a short history maybe they are
probably always
contributing to this yes
i agree but now luckily there's your
book and then if students have graduated
and they still miss some of these
qualities you could say well
what we should read is this book and
then let's let's come back to the book a
bit
because we also want to talk about the
other two qualities that we haven't
talked about
and one of them reliability and i think
reliability is interesting because i
think
it falls a bit in between the the
things we've discussed because in a
sense reliability is measurable
you can say this server is up for 99.9
of the time but on the other hand it is
harder to
predict because we can't really
calculate
how how often the server is up because
you know it might go down tomorrow for
10 days and then everything is different
again so reliability is
in the middle so so what do you consider
to be reliability and
and please give us another juicy
anecdote where stuff went wrong because
we love to hear that
yeah so yeah i agree with your
assessment it's somewhat
in between because you can basically you
can only measure reliability after the
fact
but that's kind of too late you you'd
like to measure it uh
beforehand and once again you have some
proxies here some proxy measures that
you can take beforehand
for example uh testing coverage is is
the measure that
that comes to mind that's a proxy that
you can measure
before deployment that it's a
rough indication of of reliability it's
one of the few things you can measure
that's
related to reliability at least so in
the book i checked
two different points of view so i have
two chapters about reliability
one is is called reliability through
monitoring
and by that i basically mean what's
commonly known as defensive programming
or rather an expanded form of defensive
programming because usually by defensive
programming you mean
checking preconditions of methods at
runtime basically that's that's the
basic
that's the basic version of defensive
programming but that's only a part of
uh of a larger framework that's called
the design by contract
with a more general idea and uh within
this idea
you also have invariance class
invariants and
you have post conditions so if you're
really serious about
uh reliability and you want to achieve
that
through monitoring so through online
checking
that everything is going fine then you
may want to also check
invariance while the program is running
and you may also want to check
post conditions while the program is
running
so every method checks that it's called
with the right parameters
that's its precondition then it checks
that
the the current object is in the right
state
before it starts that that's checking
the invariant
and then after uh the method finishes
its job
it also checks that it's that the method
itself has done its job
properly which sounds kind of crazy
because you're
writing both the method and the
procedure that checks that the method is
correct
but but sometimes sometimes it can be
useful but
it's very expensive in terms of uh
both time and space most of the time if
you want to add all these checks
so this kind of of extreme defensive
programming is reserved for
a special context where let's say
safety critical applications it can be
software for an industrial plant
software for
the automotive industry health
industry those applications where a bug
could be catastrophic could lead to
uh loss of life or loss of
huge amounts of money huge huge damage
and in this respect since i'm talking
about safety critical software let me
also mention that
you can speaking of this
reliability techniques you can also have
one step further which is
a static analysis and the software
verification
that those are techniques that i've
worked on
research wise where you actually
analyze the the source code without
running the software
and you try to prove formally
mathematically certain
certain properties and that's something
i only briefly mentioned in the book
because it's a very niche specialized
area and then in the book i moved
through testing
which of course is uh the main
validation technique
everyone is using because it's
the most effective practical way to
to catch bugs and uh
once again as with all chapters i have a
short uh page span so
and and and testing has since it's
it's so widespread there's a huge
literature
on testing techniques tips and tricks
and so on so
my chapter is just a brief introduction
to
unit testing techniques because i'm
always focusing on a small
unit of code and then i i point to
uh deeper and wider treatments
and and other books where you can uh you
you can get the details
yeah but i think what you mentioned here
is really interesting that if you
take good really good care of
reliability that comes at the cost of
time and space efficiently being
increased with all of these runtime
checks
whereas you might be more efficient
check less and depending on your domain
as you mentioned healthcare might be
something where you really want to have
that reliability whereas a game for
example there
space is more important and then okay
maybe sometimes it crashes and that's
too bad but that's a whole different
situation so it's interesting again how
qualities are all they all have
trade-offs with each other
exactly yeah that's it's there's
trade-offs everywhere that's computer
science
yeah and then the final quality that you
mentioned in the book which
is somewhat surprising to me because
it's so detailed it's threat safety
so readability is like this super
generic concept that you can apply to
almost everything within a project yes
the readability is not even limited to
code it also
holds for documentation and apis as we
talked about but threat safety is so
specific
and i would say it's somewhat related
also to reliability
so why did you decide to make threat
safety its own quality rather than
integrated it
into reliability right yeah you're
absolutely right
so thread safety stands out uh as
a little different than than the others
and
first of all as you say at first sight
at least it's
uh it's uh more specific than the others
it's
uh like up until a few years ago it
would have been
considered really a very specific
quality but these days
as you know uh more and more software
is inherently concurrent and that's
because of
hardware development where every machine
is concurrent these days it's actually
parallel these days
and computers are not getting faster not
getting much faster in a single core
point of view so more and more software
is becoming concurrent so i think threat
safety is going to
become more and more important and
should be considered almost as important
as
those other qualities but of course it's
it's a part of reliability
so threat safety is about uh
having a class able to having your class
able to be used by several threads
at the same time without data races
which which means without unexpected
behaviors
without getting into an inconsistent
state
and also i have to admit another reason
why i put it there it's because it fits
very well with my recurring example we
haven't talked about it
i'll just say a few words the recurring
example is
a simple very i hope very intuitive
water container example you have a
system of water containers you can pour
water into one containers into one
container and you can connect different
containers with the so-called pipes
with imaginary pipes and when you pour
water into one container this
water that you pour should disperse
equally among all containers that are
connected to this one
among all containers that you have
previously connected to this one with
pipes
and that i think turns out to be a very
interesting
example and it's very tricky to make it
thread safe so i have to admit another
reason why i
chose this particular quality besides
the fact
that it's becoming more and more
important every day
is that it fits very well with this
example because it's very tricky to make
this water container class thread safe
and it allows me to talk about different
uh
synchronization techniques including
lock-free synchronization
which is a pretty advanced topic
so the final thing i want to talk about
and this is p people that listen to my
episodes often they know this
topic always comes up and that's the
topic of different
programming languages so you mentioned
these qualities and
and the tips in your book are they as
applicable in let's say haskell
as they are in node.js or is it the case
that they fit a little bit more
with certain languages or paradigms than
they fit with others
right so on the positive side i would
say that the overall message of the book
is completely general and the overall
message as i
said several times is about being aware
of these different
forces that pull your software in
different directions being aware that
you're always
choosing a trade-off you cannot optimize
all of them at the same time there's
there's trade-offs as usual in computer
science you have to pick
a trade-off and but before that you have
to be aware of these different
dimensions of quality
and this i think is completely general
and could be useful to
someone programming in any language
the specific techniques on the other
hand that i uh
described in the book are mostly about
object oriented programming
languages so not just java but certainly
c sharp
because that's as you know it's very
similar to java and in fact
i have little sidebars here and there in
the book
relating my java techniques to
the their c-sharp counterparts
but with a little effort most of those
techniques can be
used and applied as they are in
i would say any object oriented language
if you move to a completely different
paradigm if you move to haskell or
functional programming or i don't know
logic
programming then of course the qualities
are still there
but the techniques you use to optimize
those qualities to improve those
qualities are
quite different and do you think some
programming languages
also make inherent decisions of some
qualities over other qualities
yeah sure different languages are
useful different things which means that
they emphasize
some quality over others
for example java and c-sharp the two
languages that are
explicitly mentioned in in the book they
were born
with one of the main
design objectives of those languages was
simplicity and ease of learning
so which translates to having a pretty
good readability
and also pretty good reliability for
example
just because they are garbage collected
that's
somehow improves then it tends to
improve uh reliability
of the code of course that was uh that
was
one of the design objectives 20 years
ago when
when java started but of course then it
evolved
and nowadays it's not as simple as it
was 20 years ago so
it moved a little bit uh away from its
initial simplicity
now you have all new new stuff to be
to stay modern and to keep to to to stay
modern
in the face of uh new languages and
of course there's kind of a competition
between different programming languages
on the other hand uh well to mention
another object or in the language like c
plus plus c plus plus has a very
different
uh objectives very different history so
it
uh it aims at succinctness
it aims at the highest possible
performance
in line with its predecessor c
and so it tends to you can achieve the
highest possible performance
you can basically write software as fast
as as
the hardware allows but you may lose
you you lose some readability for
example and and therefore some
maintainability
so a simple way to to look at this is to
to look at this the difference between c
plus plus and java and c sharp is look
at the amount of symbols they use
so in c plus plus you you have a lot
more symbols
you have a lot more meanings for the
symbols like
colon semicolon or dot a lot more
meanings for the symbol
and in fact you even have a operator
overload when you can give your plus
and your minus any meaning at all that
you want
so there's lots of meanings for symbols
that that helps succinctness
but it tends to decrease readability
because you
you you read a plus b and you don't know
what the plus
means you have to go figure out what the
plus between those two object means
that's this is a simple example and then
of course uh there's
uh thousands of languages focusing on
different things
like uh most functional languages have
very strong
type systems and those type systems tend
to
improve reliability once again
some people say that if your functional
program compiles then it's
a quote unquote correct so yeah that's
the experience of many people uh
programming in functional uh languages
you know the
you have your type system is so powerful
that your compiler can check
a lot more things than than than
an object-oriented compiler and so you
have a lot more checks done beforehand
by the compiler and a lot fewer
runtime errors and of course you have
more specific languages like let me
mention just one example like
go google's go language which has some
special
machinery for concurrency so it
certainly helps
make thread safe software for instance
because it has this
special communication channels between
between threads
that help avoid race conditions and so
on now of course
there's the list goes on and on
so to summarize the trade-offs between
these qualities are
language independent they always exist
however if you're choosing a language
then one language might
value a certain quality like go might
value something and hashgraph might
value something else well some
languages might value speed some
languages might value readability
so in choosing a language there's
definitely differences but once you're
in a paradigm
there will always be this tradeoff
between space and reliability
and these things are almost always at
all sweet each other right yeah
indeed great well that
i think we covered everything i wanted
to ask do you think there's anything we
missed anything that you wanted to add
to this episode
no i think it was uh great i really
enjoyed our
discussion it was great yeah i think it
also helped me clarify
certain points great but thanks we'll
make sure that we post a link of course
to the book
in the show notes so people can check it
out if they want to are they
are there any other places on the
internet where people might want to
follow you or keep up to date with other
things that you're doing
i mostly use twitter and my home page
so if people google my name they will
get
pretty quickly to my home page and then
they can also find my twitter
handle yeah we and we can also add those
to the show notes so your twitter handle
and website we can make sure that
they're linked with the episodes so
people can find it easily
that's great well thanks for being on
the show
thank you very much for having me this
is felina for software engineering radio
a helping hand with your system's
architecture software mill will help you
design high-throughput back-ends and
event-driven solutions
we're a brand trusted by businesses and
valued by employees due to our remote
first transparent organization which
gives back to the it community through
education and open source
have an idea let's code together meet
our scala java kafka and typescript
engineers at softwaremill.com today
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at
se radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on linkedin
facebook twitter or through our slack
channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening